<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Relation of a strange apparition in an ale-house next doore to the White Horse, against Sommerset-House in the Strand; where a company of papists were at their exercises as is conceived the Devill in an ugly black shape disturbing them, and tearing the rugge, and scattering it in pieces up and down the room. With a relation of a iudgement that strangely fell upon one at Mr. Mundayes house in Little Brittaine; who whilst he was cursing of Mr. Burton, Mr. Prinne, and doctor Bastwicke, his eares fell a bleeding, to the amazement of the beholders.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92351</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873082</idno>
  <idno type="VID">125536</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240943221</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E180_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873082</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99873082e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 31:E180[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Relation of a strange apparition in an ale-house next doore to the White Horse, against Sommerset-House in the Strand; where a company of papists were at their exercises as is conceived the Devill in an ugly black shape disturbing them, and tearing the rugge, and scattering it in pieces up and down the room. With a relation of a iudgement that strangely fell upon one at Mr. Mundayes house in Little Brittaine; who whilst he was cursing of Mr. Burton, Mr. Prinne, and doctor Bastwicke, his eares fell a bleeding, to the amazement of the beholders.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Smethrust,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A piece of Puritan propaganda against the Catholics in the form of a colorful journalistic account of alleged supernatural interference with a papist meeting and the seizure of one who slandered three celebrated Puritans."--note of bookseller, Stonehill.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Apparitions --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  England --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125536:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF A STRANGE APPARITION In an Ale-house next doore to the <hi>White Horse,</hi> against <hi>Sommerset-House</hi> in the Strand; Where a company of Papists were at their Exercises: as is conceived the Devill in an ugly black shape disturbing them, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>the Rugge, and scattering it in pleces up and down the Roome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH A RELATION</hi> Of a Iudgement that strangely fell upon one at Mr. <hi>Mundayes</hi> House in <hi>Little Brittaine;</hi> who whilst he was cursing of Mr. <hi>Burton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Bastwicke,</hi> his eares fell <hi>a bleeding, to the amazement of the beholders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Smethrust,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb facs="tcp:125536:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125536:2"/>
            <head>A STRANGE APPA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition at an Alehouse next doore to the <hi>White Horse</hi> against Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset House in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertain Jesuites or Papists, being met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at an Alehouse in the Strand, neare the White Horse over against Sommerset House; they were at their Exercises in an upper Chamber, three stories high, they were most of them <hi>Irish;</hi> who whilest they were at the exercise, with what zeal, I shall not need to relate, because it is too well known what Popish zeal is.</p>
            <p>But see how exactly they conjured with their Beads (as I may so call it) for without all doubt it was either the Devil or some strange Monster, that disturbed them from the Devill.</p>
            <p>There was in the roome where they were a bed, and under the window against the beds feet, stood a back Chaire of Red leather.</p>
            <p>And after their long and loud acclamations, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125536:3"/>Popish exercises, there appeared amongst them a strange Monster: or if you will the Devill in the shape of a Monster, all as black as pitch, as bigge as a great Dogge; which appeared in a most horrid shape, to the affrightment of all the company; which disturbed the company exceedingly; then they crost themselves, and applyed them to their Popish Customes.</p>
            <p>But the black Fiend leaped into the Chaire that stood by the window, at the beds feet, and there roused it self up; which made them all to quake and tremble. It put them out of the tale of their Beads, and made them to run some one way, and some another, and set the whole house in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straction.</p>
            <p>Amongst the rest, one of them (an <hi>Irish</hi> man) drew out his Rapier, and with a great rage began to scuffle with this strange Monster: and between hope and fear ran desperately at him; but it leaped down from the Chaire in a furions manner, and immediately got upon the bed, which was covered with a green Rugge.</p>
            <p>This Fiend toare the Rugge all to peeces, and threw it up and down the roome: and many peeces of it was found upon the floore. And those that were then present were so amazed hereat, that they knew not how the vision vanished, or what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of it; one of the servants of the house ranne forth of the doore to a neighbours, quaking and shivering at what she had seen: but one of them, seeing her in such a fright, laboured to perswade her that it was a dogge: Lord blesse me from such
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125536:3"/>dogges (quoth she) but they could not soon paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie her, to mitigate her fear.</p>
            <p>Neighbours hearing of it, enquiring concerning it, the people of the house report it to be a mighty Cat: the Papists report it to be a dogge: but mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people have resorted thither, to enquire of it; and to talk with the people about this vision which so disturbed them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="relation">
            <head>A RELATION Of a strange Iudgement at the House of Master MUNDAY in <hi>Little Brittaine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TWo Gentlemen were talking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about news, and such like dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course at the house of one M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes</hi> in <hi>Little Britaine,</hi> who at the last fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Discourse about Religion. Then they fell into discourse of M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Burton,</hi> M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. <hi>Prinne,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Bastwikey,</hi> and of their sufferings: the one of them applauding them for honest godly, religious men, and such as suffered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125536:4"/>patiently; and were faithfull witnesses of Iesus Christ, commending them to be such as he verily thought were the Children of God.</p>
            <p>But the other answered: Oh you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived man, they are Scismaticall Fellows; it is no matter if they were hanged: a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of base <hi>Brownists,</hi> as we are troubled with a company of them; they are base dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling fellows.</p>
            <p>Oh! I pray you, said the other, be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> so hot, I beleeve that they are such as are reall honest men, and such as have stood for Christ from their very heart, as witnesse may testifie.</p>
            <p>But the other answered (cursing them) and all such Puritans (as he called them) If <hi>Burton,</hi> quoth he, had had a Bishopricke, and had beene made a Bishop, (quoth he) he had never found fault with that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>No, quoth the other man, you are mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; what he did or any of them, I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily perswaded that they did out of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that they were men truly fearing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125536:4"/>God; oh the weeping eyes that beheld them when they lost their cares, and the tender hearts that pittied them then, and ever since; methinks it grieves me to thinke of it: Push (quoth the other, swearing a bloody oath) It were no matter if they had beene hanged, base scismaticall Iacks, to trouble the whole Kingdome with their base opinions, and he concluded that saying with bloody, and fearefull Curses.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, on an instant, he began to sweat, and to be faint, and taking out of his pocket, an hankercher, to wipe his face and his head, a strange Iudgement fell upon him, his eares fell a bleeding, and thereby his handkercher was all bloody with wiping of them; which wrought a strange amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all that stood by.</p>
            <p>Oh! therefore, let every one beware how they curse Gods people; for the righteous God judgeth iustly, and will avenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe on those that rise up against him, and his distressed Saints.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>